<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>kolage</title><link>https://jan-kolarik.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on kolage</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jan-kolarik.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About</title><link>https://jan-kolarik.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jan-kolarik.github.io/about/</guid><description>About me</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My name is Jan Kolárik and I&rsquo;m a software engineer currently working in Red Hat.</p>
<p>I first discovered Linux when I was 14 years old and a few years later I started using it as my main operating system.</p>
<p>Recently, I&rsquo;ve entered the world of open source as a developer, which has been my dream for a long time.</p>
<p>I have experience mainly with C++, C# and Python languages and I love applying test-driven development principles in my projects wherever it&rsquo;s possible. Currently I am also discovering the beauties of Rust.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>DNF5 at FOSDEM</title><link>https://jan-kolarik.github.io/posts/dnf5-fosdem2023/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jan-kolarik.github.io/posts/dnf5-fosdem2023/</guid><description>Presenting the upcoming Fedora Linux package manager in Brussels</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/images/fosdem-logo.png" alt="fosdem-logo"  title="FOSDEM logo"  />
</p>
<p>Last weekend I&rsquo;ve attended FOSDEM 2023 conference with my colleagues from the Red Hat RPM software management team. We gave a talk about the DNF5 package manager which will be the new default in Fedora Linux soon.</p>
<p>It was the first time for me speaking in public at such a huge event and it was really exciting. This whole meetup was very energizing. Lot of different positive vibes from various tracks. I hope I&rsquo;ll make it there again next year.</p>
<p>If you are more interested, you can visit <a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/dnf5/">this</a> link and see a recording of our presentation or any other talk from the conference.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>